so it's November 14th a pentagon partner
Emily Oberman is just a real Dan you
eyed enemy system for Warner Brothers
entertainment a bold slender emblem
replaces the fat heavy multi-layered
mess they add for years paired with a
fun cartoonish type paste a new identity
is just on point but nothing can be
perfect showing off the new dynamic logo
as it's often done they include a
technical breakdown of its formal
qualities as if people would actually
appreciate and in doing so they further
one of the biggest lies in the sphere of
design the golden ratio blessed with an
eighth divine like beauty these perfect
shapes or more accurately their
proportions has said to be the secret
behind a lot of the Vinci's most iconic
masterpieces the Greek pantheon and
interestingly enough Apple's new logo
but how can a strict system of
proportions be the underlying reason why
such a diverse set of works looks
aesthetically pleasing
the answer is deceptively simple it's
not technically speaking two quantities
that are in golden ratio if their ratio
is equal to the ratio of their Sun to
the larger of the two quantities as this
makes sense to virtually no one there's
an easier way to say two shapes are in a
golden ratio if one divided by the other
equals roughly 1.618
mathematically this ratio seems like a
pretty cool concept who kept many
thinkers busy for a long time but ever
since equipped this way back into art
and design people started making wild
claims about its efficacy there's a lot
of tutorials out there that help you
build the shapes needed to design in the
golden ratio here's a popular way to do
it we take a square and duplicate it we
do it again only this time we make the
new squares tall as the two initial
squares stacked on top of each other we
take the whole composition and repeat
the process here these two squares are
now in the golden ratio except they're
not
in fact this way of building the pallet
for your golden shapes is off by quite a
lot we can check by taking the big
square and dividing its proportions by
1.618 if the pallet have been built
correctly the new square will be the
same size as the smaller one but there's
an evident gap between the two this is
because what we've built here is
actually a visual representation of
Fibonacci sequence which tends towards
the golden ratio but it's not actually
the same especially with smaller numbers
here's an actual golden ratio palette if
we take the bigger square and divide
these proportions by 1.618
we can see the two squares do overlap I
guess the main takeaway here is if you
really want to use the golden ratio in
your designs at least make sure you're
doing it correctly now that we've
established that most people using the
golden ratio are probably off by a
substantial margin let's get to the main
point the golden ratio is
there's nothing special about this
rectangle that would make any design
structure around it more aesthetically
pleasing regardless of their context and
overall quality here's a set of 4
rectangles it has to pick a favorite
which one would you choose do you even
have a favor and they just rectangles
what makes this one so divine
even if the golden ratio were to be
somehow more palatable when it's the
figures who rely on a few rules are we
saying we can just arrange any of these
shapes however we want and the result
will be guaranteed to illustrate my
point let's look at this popular
wireframe for the Apple logo here we see
the icon broken down to a set of golden
circles the overlap to shape the curves
of the design disregarding the many
imprecisions thought it throughout the
whole wireframe the salient question is
is there a specific reason why we would
have to pick these specific circles and
build the logo this way instead of this
way well we say we can just mix and
match without any rules at all who would
ever build an organic refined shape from
the inside out
by packing smaller geometries next to
each other seemingly at random here's
the same logo build with a range of
different proportions could you tell
which one was designed with the golden
shapes the simple fact that I could
arrange the golden shapes are very
pleased while making this logo should
make the task impossible this gets to
the paradox behind the golden ratio as
long as we play with scale literally any
shape could be built using geometries
with golden proportions as it turns out
the iteration following the 1.618 rule
is actually the worst
the main question now becomes how could
it be possible that the myth still lives
on centuries after its conception in one
of the biggest design firms in the world
I tend to think it's mostly marketing at
least in the upper echelons a big-budget
client will literally drool over your
design when you take the time to explain
why it belongs to the same category of
refined masterpieces as the Mona Lisa
back in the real world the design team
probably did their own thing and then
reverse engineered the golden ratio into
the shape it's a cool story is ancient
and somewhat arcane and so it sells as
for everyone else Beauty can be
streamlined into a rule it can depend on
a set ratio and it won't be boxed in by
charts or wireframes balanced
composition are as pleasing as their
while loose counterparts graphic design
is filled with examples of situations
where sturdy ametrine yields a worse
result than just eyeballing it typefaces
are built with optical Corrections to
make them feel balanced center type in
shapes are often offset because the way
we perceive things is actually not that
mathematically accurate as long as you
know your craft no chart will ever
guarantee a better result across the
board good taste is what you got an
informed design process not a loosely
applied mathematical principle let's all
get together and finally put this myth
to rest thank you
you